<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sean Kolk - Community Builder &amp; Explorer</title>
    <description>Bringing people together to create more than they could have alone</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 07:48:53 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 07:48:53 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Racing Around Vancouver Island - The VanIsle 360 Experience</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While still green to the waters of the Salish and wanting to lean my back into racing, I found myself in my third year in Puget Sound with an invitation to sail the outside of Vancouver Island by way of racing the whole entity. In the spring of 2024, my partner and I joined the Race to Alaska with Team Natural Disaster on the Olsen 30 ‘Wildfire’ and delivered our home, the Catalina 36 ‘Petrichor’ to Ketchikan before taking her up to Glacier Bay and then back to Seattle by September. It was half a year of sailing and more preparation than that, and only left us yearning for more. So when the owner of Golux, whom we had sailed with before and even met briefly cruising in the San Juans, offered me a role on their new vessel to sail around the outside of the Island, I couldn’t resist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Race That Brings Communities Together
The VanIsle 360 has been a Canadian staple, envisioned by Jeff and Sylvia Motley as a way to bring together sailors and the coastal communities of Vancouver Island. It’s a continuation in the tradition of sailors going around objects on a map, but this race is something more ambitious than most weekend regattas. The race begins and concludes in Nanaimo, the industrial capital of the island, comprising nine stages with start lines, finish lines, and overnight moorage. Some legs include lay days; others start the morning after. Many take competitors into town community centers for lunch or dinner, holding fundraisers for local schools along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The racing itself demands intentional preparation. Teams must meet “offshore Level 2” race requirements for both crew and vessel, carrying storm sails, auxiliary navigation lights, and a range of offshore life jackets and foul weather gear not found on buoy day races. The course requires both short tacking through the Johnstone Strait and navigating Pacific swell from Winter Harbor to Ucluelet - a 140-nautical-mile passage that takes many teams over 30 hours to complete. At around 580 nautical miles total, it’s both a lengthy event and a standard to rise up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building the Team and Learning the Beast
In spite of all these requirements, year after year sailors rise to the occasion. As we’ve found sailing the Salish, and in climbing the peaks of the Coastal Pacific, various groups organize themselves around a challenge - whether that be an offshore race, a rally, or a boat project. They take their boats out to compete and explore, and the circles start small, then get larger and larger. There’s a race almost every night of the week by the first day of spring in the Seattle area: going around three to four marks on a Monday afternoon, to a far-off buoy or island on weekends, evolving into races touching the Juan de Fuca over a weekend, and eventually out to the Pacific via the 100-year-old tradition of the Swiftsure race from Victoria to Neah Bay - with the VanIsle 360 on its heels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met as a crew in early March to establish our training schedule, race availability, and resource commitments covering food, hotels, transport, and anything else that needed expectation setting. The challenge was immediate: the owners had only acquired the sailboat in January, and we were still unpacking the various systems, working out how she would perform. The 36-ton aluminum vessel was going to be the heaviest in the fleet, and we all needed to understand her strengths and weaknesses. Our team would be five hands per leg, with two of us switching out about halfway through the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to work out how to tack with running backstays on the 70-foot rig with square-top main, determine how to use the furling foresail with electric furler, and decide whether to use a fixed inner forestay or a removable option. Every system had to be examined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Art of Crew Dynamics
Captain and crew dynamics require constant development. While lines, blocks, and runners are theoretically similar to other boats, they’re necessarily specific and require practice and muscle memory to hoist, haul, set, and tack effectively. Our Monday races became ‘practice,’ with room to make small mistakes and continually shake out the boat. Our weekends grew longer and more competitive, testing where our strategies would pay off or leave us sitting in a wind hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spreadsheets were made, cost recording applications established, hotels and ferries and restaurants booked. We modified clutches, the electrical system, the jack lines, and the lazy jacks. Before we knew it, we were up in Victoria preparing for our first overnight, with myself set up to roam the Island for the next 20 days between races and days climbing peaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into the Fray
The 0900 start time for Swiftsure commenced in a light wind kerfuffle, but soon we were off alongside many of the boats we’d be sailing with over the next three weeks. The fleet ranged from 15-person crewed TP52s like Smoke, Mist, and The Shadow II with their hefty support vans and tightly scoped roles, to the fastship Ripple, which Chris and Jason Wolf helm in multi-day races with only the two of them, switching every 15 minutes at the helm while actively trimming their kites and setting course records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few days in Nanaimo set the tone for everything that followed. All competitors were rafted up on a long pier, which allowed everyone to peer into each other’s vessels and learn about projects, problems, previous races, and issues on the rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting to Nanaimo from Seattle by way of Victoria is no small effort in itself. At least one boat had already grounded, and another’s black water system had unleashed itself upon the bilge, resulting in undesirable projects for the crew. The official start was early Saturday, but the skippers meeting followed by the road crew meeting meant everyone was there Friday evening, if not before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Upwind Battles
When racing finally began, the first legs proved to be strong upwind battles. These conditions pushed lighter boats back while allowing heavier ships to crash through the whitecaps with their weight advantage. Current is always a factor in the Salish Sea - it can push up to 15 knots out of Seymore Narrows, affecting boats all the way down to Campbell River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself pulling weight into the crank as fast as we could, tacking our beast of a boat and experimenting with our inner forestay while green water crashed over the bow. We’d spot our marks and play defense, blocking and staying above other boats. Sometimes there’d be a current line to exploit - let’s go for that and expand our lead. We performed well enough to inspire conversation about our rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each evening after racing, the support vans would arrive to shuttle supplies for boats without onboard quarters: hauling sails, cushions, food, sleeping bags, and often crew to hotels. Teams would visit each other to congratulate good sailing or check if a boat was okay after a sail blew or some mishap occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always a balance between focusing on your own vessel and engaging with the fleet; a small politics of deciding boat priorities versus personal ones. We ate aboard and had berths for everyone, yet we’d still booked hotel rooms for showers and space often desired after the pressure of racing together all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Port Hardy: Gateway to the Pacific
Port Hardy marks a significant transition point. It’s the northernmost port on the island worth mentioning for supplies and safe harbor, and the place where many crews swap out after a week of sailing. Here, boats prepare for the Pacific swell that will influence their race thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The legs ahead would be long for many boats, with time to see the sunrise before finishing and allowing for a full day’s rest after 20+ hour sails. But Port Hardy also marked where the small dramas began to unfold - both between boats and within crews. Grievances about tactics being too close or unfair would arise. Who said what about which boat, or how polite someone was at dinner became topics of conversation. Nothing uncommon, but still humorous to observe when this is all voluntary participation in what amounts to a big game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into the Wild Pacific
Humpback whales were spotted regularly, otters became common sights, and eagles were an everyday occurrence. The outside waters provided shearwaters, storm petrels, albatross, and the occasional puffin! We hit speeds in the high 30s, 20 miles offshore on our way down to Ucluelet, surfing at 18 knots with the peaks of Vancouver Island coming in and out of sight in the 20-foot swell. Grey fog would blow in and out as we attempted to find the current that could provide a knot or two over the next ten hours - enough to push us ahead. It’s both intense and peaceful out here. The Steller sea lions seem to agree as they bob in the waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the sun set, we began tracking the moon for navigation. The digital compass reacted too slowly, the wind vane mounted so high that finding the feel took more time than expected. Having a reference, any reference, helped enormously. A star, a mountain, another ship. We settled into our rhythm: one hour at the helm, one hour on a sheet, one hour asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Night Passage: Where Wild Things Are
The routine was smooth and consistent, yet every wave crest looked like a breaching whale in the moonlight. There’s a level of anxiety mixed with creativity that needs to be managed. ‘It’s okay, we’ve been at this for hours. If it’s really an anomaly, ask your crew to verify.’ This is a landscape from where the wild things are, and we had joined them in part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morning brought clarity to our navigation as pinks and oranges edged into existence. We’d been up and down all night, and light winds put everyone on edge as we closed on the finish. We were so close, but moving at only 2 knots in choppy water near rocks had us all tense with each other. Can we jibe now, or should we get just a little closer for better velocity made good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind filled in with the dawn, and suddenly we were moving again. The final approach to Ucluelet became a blur of focused energy - trimming sails, calling out rocks and other boats as we converged on the finish. The relief was palpable as we crossed, not just from completing this brutal leg, but from proving ourselves capable of handling whatever the Pacific would give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Transformation
We rafted up with the other finishers in a harbor that felt like home after our time in Alaska, sharing stories from our night passage, and seeing who needed help with a project, or could meet for coffee and a hike the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we worked our way back around the island over the following days, completing the final legs through increasingly familiar waters, the full scope of what we’d accomplished began to sink in. This race had become more than just a test of sailing skill - it was an exploration of pushing boundaries, both personal and nautical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VanIsle 360 strips away the comfortable predictability of weekend racing and throws you into the raw reality of ocean sailing, where decisions carry consequences for the fortnight ahead. The sea receives your respect and attention, given or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we crossed the finish line back in Nanaimo - 580 nautical miles and three weeks later - we weren’t the same crew that had started. We’d been changed by the experience, bonded by shared challenges, and humbled by the magnificent power of the waters surrounding Vancouver Island. The circles had indeed grown larger, and we were already planning our return to these waters for another round of testing ourselves against the Island’s embrace.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sailing,/racing,/vancouver-island,/offshore/2025/08/14/vanisle-360.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sailing,/racing,/vancouver-island,/offshore/2025/08/14/vanisle-360.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>sailing,</category>
        
        <category>racing,</category>
        
        <category>vancouver-island,</category>
        
        <category>offshore</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bring People Together, Explore, Share, and Make Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bring people together, explore, share, and make things.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Craig Mod just kept making and doing, and putting things in public places… you can too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I woke up on a dirt road, and tonight I sleep in a dirt parking lot. In between there were ferries, abandon mines, electrical fixes, and brief encounters with graduated ski patrollers. I’ve driven from Campbell River up to Mt. Cain by way of Quadra Island and its wonderful little Cafe Aroma. Flo and Andrew told us I’d like it there; and yet I’m concerned that there isn’t… an obvious school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-listened-to-on-the-drive&quot;&gt;What I Listened To on the Drive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the drive I listened to Hank Green tell MIT that what they do is Make, but what gives them hope is other people. I listened Craig Mod tell Rich Roll about his love of walks and how he packs them all in; how the Japanese have this word: &lt;strong&gt;YUTORI&lt;/strong&gt; which means to have the space to have peace of mind; and how that can only come from having the ability to take risks and not crash: which he calls a safety net. The Japanese have universal health care, and don’t bankrupt their people and that’s how they can compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also talked about teaching the youth about what they can do; taking very long walks 1 week at a time, and one month at a time; only focusing on the now; and writing every night 2-3k words. I’m trying that now to see how much I can write; what I can do, and what even ½ an hour takes me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-creating-and-shipping&quot;&gt;On Creating and Shipping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m envious of Craig; not that I want to be him. His life sounds very hard; but that he produced and created, and put it out there. He created. He &lt;strong&gt;CREATED&lt;/strong&gt;; and &lt;strong&gt;SHIPPED&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would it look like to make the write up of working with small groups towards an end? What would it look like to be vulnerable enough to ask questions and talk to the people in the room? To be the goof and to connect, learn, and share?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-framework-for-leading&quot;&gt;A Framework for Leading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The framework would look like: The Tao of leading; meeting people where they are and helping them get where they want to go. It’s understanding, approaching, agreeing, and striving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the book of John; learn how to ‘resource’ people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written from a dirt parking lot on Vancouver Island, experimenting with Craig Mod’s practice of writing 2-3k words every night, seeing what half an hour of focused writing can produce.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/community,/making,/reflection,/travel/2025/06/14/yutori.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/community,/making,/reflection,/travel/2025/06/14/yutori.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>community,</category>
        
        <category>making,</category>
        
        <category>reflection,</category>
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Finding Your Gaps and Working with Teams - Lessons from the Cockpit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m writing this from Flo and Andrew’s place after another weekend racing aboard Golux, still processing what happened out there. My legs are finally warming up, and I’m thinking about gaps - not the ones between my foul weather gear that let the cold in, but the knowledge gaps that racing exposes so brutally and quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something about being on deck in 20 knots of wind, trying to reef the main while spray crashes over the bow, that strips away any illusions about what you know versus what you think you know. This weekend taught me as much about working with teams as it did about sail trim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-authority-meets-learning&quot;&gt;When Authority Meets Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched Jake work with Holm on sailing techniques, and it struck me how much easier coaching becomes when you come from a position of clear authority. Jake has the experience, the knowledge, and most importantly, the confidence to say “here’s what we need to do” when things get complicated. But where does that leave the rest of us who are still figuring things out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake took the time to answer what I’m sure were obvious questions, hopping up to adjust the traveler in a way that surprised Holm, then explaining why we needed to travel down but not sheet out. He gave Holm the confidence to trust his crew while learning to drive the boat better. That’s coaching - meeting someone where they are and helping them get where they want to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more interesting question is how the rest of us contribute when we’re not the expert in the room. I realized it starts with forming a group mentality around better questions. Instead of pretending to know things I don’t, I’ve been trying to frame what we want to accomplish and what we can improve on, then share those observations with everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-technical-reality-check&quot;&gt;The Technical Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racing taught me quickly where my sail trim knowledge ended. I’d been sailing for years but still struggled with the basics when conditions got serious. The main sail, I learned, needs constant attention - letting off to point up, sheeting in to take on more wind, adjusting for every puff and header. Those top two tell tales on the trailing edge? They’re supposed to flutter about half the time. Nobody had ever told me that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foresail seemed simpler at first - set it with the cars, trim for your point of sail, and you’re mostly done except for tacking. But even there, I had assumptions about light and heavy air positioning that turned out to be wrong. Smaller sails want to be further forward, larger sails further back. If you see stalls, change and adjust. Simple in theory, harder when you’re cranking winches that need four wraps just to catch the load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept notes throughout the weekend because I knew I’d forget the details. The running backstay winches need to be completely off when they’re loose because they don’t slide well. The main halyard slips in the clutch, so you over-tighten slightly and watch it drop an inch. For reefing, you stop the crinkle about a foot above the boom, release the vang, and let the main sheet run until it’s completely loose - there will be friction, more than you expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t the kind of details you learn from books or YouTube videos. They’re boat-specific, crew-specific, and they only make sense when you’re doing them under pressure with people who know what they’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-feedback-loop&quot;&gt;The Feedback Loop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we finished, I sent Beth and Holm a message asking for feedback on how I did, what I could improve, and what I should do less of. It felt vulnerable to ask directly, but I realized that’s exactly the gap I needed to close. Too often we assume we know where we stand instead of actively seeking input from people who were watching us work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weekend had clear highs and lows that told their own story. Understanding how main sail trim actually works felt like a breakthrough, as did finally grasping inside versus outside jibes on the asymmetrical spinnaker. Going through a complete reefing process while racing gave me confidence I hadn’t had before. The sunset and sunrise reminded me why we do this in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my legs were cold again despite wearing everything I owned - socks, boots, leggings, foul weather gear over a warm upper body. I still haven’t figured out the heat management puzzle for overnight racing. Maybe I just need to accept that foot warmers and back warmers aren’t luxuries but necessities, and stop trying to tough it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgment-as-team-building&quot;&gt;Acknowledgment as Team Building&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me most was how differently the weekend felt when we took time to acknowledge each other’s contributions. Beth worked hard to bring the team together and make sure we took care of ourselves. That’s not sailing technique, but it’s what made everything else possible. Molly is heading off to sail the Great Lakes this summer with a new team, and hearing Jake’s stories about their time together reminded me that these relationships extend far beyond any single race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of acknowledgment isn’t just politeness - it’s how teams build the trust they need when things get difficult. When you’re surfing down swells at 18 knots and someone needs to make a quick decision about sail trim, you want to be sailing with people who’ve proven they care about the outcome and about each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beyond-the-boat&quot;&gt;Beyond the Boat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep thinking about how these lessons apply everywhere teams come together under pressure. Whether you’re working on marine conservation in the North Salish, building software, or organizing community events, the same patterns emerge. Some people have clear authority based on experience and knowledge. Others contribute through curiosity, careful observation, and willingness to do the work that needs doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gaps you find today - technical, interpersonal, or otherwise - become the foundation for what you bring tomorrow. Jake worked with Holm from authority, but the rest of us work from questions, contribution, and the willingness to learn. Both are essential when you’re trying to accomplish something challenging together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racing strips away comfortable assumptions and forces you to confront what you actually know versus what you think you know. But it also shows you how much faster you can learn when you’re working with people who are invested in the outcome and willing to share what they’ve figured out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cold legs will eventually warm up. The knowledge gaps, with enough curiosity and good people to learn from, start filling themselves in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written from Salt Spring Island, preparing for another season aboard Golux and thinking about how the lessons from the cockpit apply everywhere teams come together to achieve something challenging.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sailing,/teams,/learning,/feedback/2025/05/26/Finding-Your-Gaps.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sailing,/teams,/learning,/feedback/2025/05/26/Finding-Your-Gaps.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>sailing,</category>
        
        <category>teams,</category>
        
        <category>learning,</category>
        
        <category>feedback</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Access to Tools - A Center for Thinking Deeply About Our Situation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I stumbled across the MoMA exhibition on “Access to Tools” this week, and it stopped me cold. Not because of the artifacts or the design, but because of what it represented: a moment when someone had the audacity to create “a center for helping human beings think deeply about their situation.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Whole Earth Catalog’s “Access to Tools” section wasn’t just a shopping guide for hippies. It was something more ambitious and necessary - a curated collection of the best thinking about systems, ecology, governance, technology, and the human condition. Stewart Brand and his collaborators were attempting to bridge what they called “the cream of both the culture and the counterculture,” creating space for deep thinking about how we live and what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-made-access-to-tools-different&quot;&gt;What Made “Access to Tools” Different&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tool catalogs tell you what to buy. The Whole Earth Catalog told you how to think. Its “Access to Tools” section included books about ecological thinking on large scales, ways to understand the place of both high and low technologies in human life, approaches to governance, frameworks for thinking about business, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t random. Brand understood that tools aren’t just objects - they’re ways of thinking made manifest. A solar panel is a way of thinking about energy independence. A geodesic dome is a way of thinking about shelter and geometry. A book about systems thinking is a way of thinking about complexity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalog operated on the premise that people could learn to think systemically about their lives and communities, but they needed access to the right tools for thinking. Not just hammers and saws, but conceptual frameworks, philosophical approaches, and examples of people who had figured out different ways to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-collision-of-culture-and-counterculture&quot;&gt;The Collision of Culture and Counterculture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What strikes me most about “Access to Tools” is how it refused the false choice between embracing technology and rejecting it. The counterculture of the 1960s often positioned itself as anti-technology, anti-system, anti-establishment. But Brand and his collaborators saw that wholesale rejection of tools and systems meant giving up agency over your own life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, they asked different questions: What if we could be thoughtful about which technologies we adopted? What if we could understand systems well enough to create alternatives? What if the goal wasn’t to reject tools, but to choose better ones?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant including everything from traditional crafts to computer programming, from organic farming techniques to satellite communications. The common thread wasn’t the sophistication of the technology, but the quality of thinking behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-for-thinking-about-scale&quot;&gt;Tools for Thinking About Scale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful aspects of “Access to Tools” was its attention to scale. It included resources for thinking about personal choices (what kind of shelter, what kind of food, what kind of work), community decisions (how to organize, how to govern, how to share resources), and planetary systems (ecology, energy, interconnection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t academic systems thinking. It was practical philosophy for people who wanted to take responsibility for their impact and their choices. The catalog assumed that individuals could learn to think at multiple scales simultaneously - from the personal to the planetary - and that this kind of thinking was both possible and necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see echoes of this approach in everything from permaculture design to the maker movement to current discussions about appropriate technology and local resilience. But we’ve lost something of the ambition to create comprehensive resources for deep thinking about our situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-we-lost-and-what-we-need&quot;&gt;What We Lost and What We Need&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet was supposed to democratize access to information in ways that the Whole Earth Catalog could only dream of. And in some ways it has. But information isn’t the same as curation, and curation isn’t the same as creating frameworks for thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Access to Tools” approach required editorial judgment about what constituted good thinking, combined with the assumption that people could learn to think well about complex problems. It was optimistic about human capacity for learning and skeptical of experts who claimed exclusive access to truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have more tools than ever, but we’ve lost much of the framework for thinking about which tools to choose and why. We have endless information about systems, but less help thinking systemically. We have unprecedented access to knowledge, but fewer resources for wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools-for-our-current-situation&quot;&gt;Tools for Our Current Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would “Access to Tools” look like today? What would help us think deeply about our current situation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d need frameworks for thinking about information overload, climate change, technological disruption, community resilience, and global interconnection. We’d need tools for thinking about both individual choices and collective action. We’d need resources that bridge different ways of knowing - scientific, traditional, experiential, intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we’d need the editorial courage to distinguish between thinking that helps and thinking that doesn’t, between tools that expand human agency and tools that diminish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Whole Earth Catalog emerged from a particular moment of cultural upheaval and technological possibility. We’re living through our own moment of upheaval and possibility, with different challenges but similar needs for frameworks that help us think clearly about our choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-invitation-to-think-systemically&quot;&gt;The Invitation to Think Systemically&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find most inspiring about “Access to Tools” is its fundamental optimism about human capacity. It assumed that people could learn to think about complex systems, that they could make thoughtful choices about technology, that they could take responsibility for their impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t naive optimism. It was hard-earned wisdom about what humans are capable of when they have access to good tools for thinking and the support of communities engaged in similar questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invitation remains open: What tools do you need to think deeply about your situation? What systems do you need to understand better? What frameworks would help you make choices that align with your values?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalog is gone, but the questions it raised are more urgent than ever. We still need ways to bridge culture and counterculture, individual choice and collective action, local wisdom and global perspective. We still need centers for helping human beings think deeply about their situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the question isn’t whether someone will create a new “Access to Tools,” but whether each of us can become better curators of the tools we use for thinking about the world and our place in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The MoMA exhibition “Access to Tools” explored the legacy of the Whole Earth Catalog and its influence on design, technology, and culture. More information at: https://www.moma.org/interactives/exhibitions/2011/AccesstoTools/&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 16:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/tools,/systems,/thinking,/culture/2025/01/14/access-to-tools.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/tools,/systems,/thinking,/culture/2025/01/14/access-to-tools.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>tools,</category>
        
        <category>systems,</category>
        
        <category>thinking,</category>
        
        <category>culture</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Race to Alaska 2024 - Seven Days of Hell and Glory</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Race to Alaska is simple in concept: 750 miles from Port Townsend to Ketchikan, no engine, no support, and if you break something, you fix it yourself or you’re done. What they don’t tell you is how quickly everything can go sideways, and how much you learn about yourself when it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six hours into the race, our headstay snapped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-one-when-everything-goes-wrong&quot;&gt;Day One: When Everything Goes Wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were pedaling along Galiano Island when it happened - that sickening crack that every sailor dreads. Our rod rigging had failed up at the masthead, and suddenly we had a foresail wrapped around our boat like a metallic Christmas present nobody wanted. Brian immediately rigged spinnaker halyards to the bow deck plate as temporary forestays while we assessed the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the main down and two people pedaling against current toward the nearest island, the reality of our situation set in. We could make 1.8 to 2 knots at the expense of crew energy, switching out every 20-40 minutes. Not exactly racing speed, but we were still moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nathalie took lead on calling riggers while Brian measured what we’d need for replacement parts. Winston and I hoisted Brian up the mast to get proper measurements of the failed rigging. All of this was happening while we pedaled in flat water, slowly gaining confidence in our jury-rigged setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things started looking plausible when we coordinated with a friend we’d met at an R2AK event the year before - a previous racer known as “Super Dave” who lived near Nanaimo. The riggers had assembled a new forestay and were sending it up from Sidney. We had a plan, a destination, and surprisingly, the previous year’s winning team had heard about our situation and was heading to assist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We docked under sail and pedal power right next to what turned out to be a rigging tower - planned or not, it was exactly what we needed. Within 30 minutes we had the new rig in hand, and within three hours we had replaced the forestay, tensioned everything, and were back on the water. Jean and Ev even provided showers and a meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 6:30 in the morning when the break happened to 6:30 in the evening, we pushed off to catch our competition and make up for lost time. That night we entered the Strait of Georgia and, in honor of our new rig, tested her in 25+ knot winds on the nose, putting our crew through hell while making way toward Campbell River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-three-spinnaker-dreams-and-tidal-realities&quot;&gt;Day Three: Spinnaker Dreams and Tidal Realities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our watch schedule had us sailing four hours, resting four hours, with two hours floating between crew maintenance and sailing assistance. I awoke after a hellish night to find the wind had shifted and we were ready to set the kite. We’d made good progress overnight and could make even more if we pulled this off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting the black symmetrical spinnaker in 15 knots gusting higher was going to be sporty, but we could see Guardian Sailing in their J24 and Tips Up on their Hobie 16 ahead of us. As the kite filled, our speed jumped from 6-7 knots under jib to 8-9 knots, hitting 10-11 when we caught waves and surfed down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for the boats that had gained on us overnight, Seymour Narrows proved to be a hell of a tide gate. Even though they’d made it all the way to Campbell River, fighting 7 knots of adverse current was dangerous and futile. We made 30 miles in 4 hours, dousing the kite only to navigate around Campbell River’s complicated outflows before raising it again when the current turned in our favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The R2AK media boat caught up with us as we entered the notorious passage, filming our passage through one of the most challenging tidal areas on the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-four-the-johnstone-strait-challenge&quot;&gt;Day Four: The Johnstone Strait Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere between Seymour Narrows and the Broughtons, the Johnstone Strait develops into the most complex tidal area of the Inside Passage. Pacific winds meet currents flowing both directions, strong enough to force anchor drops in anchorages that don’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, we could pedal. Even at 1 knot, it was better than sitting idle at anchor. The trick was maintaining just enough speed to make progress without burning out the crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spotted competition at night by their anchor lights - everyone was dealing with the same light winds. We chased current edges, looking for pockets of favorable flow, trying to read the tidal surface in dull moonlight obscured by clouds. At one point we found a gentle eddy half the width of the channel that pulled us across, forcing us to loop back down and across to stay near shore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I woke up from my off-watch, the first sound I heard was “We’re match racing Pickle Train and Rock the Boat!” We had the number 1 jib up and a full main, with Team Rock the Boat barely 100 feet off our port side. All three boats were tacking back and forth in the narrows, scratching for every breath of wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pickle Train - a heavily modified Santa Cruz 27 with new keel, rudders, mast, and Kevlar-reinforced deck - could point higher than us, but our Olson 30 could bash through rough seas and fly downwind with our symmetrical spinnaker. After hours of close racing, we emerged from the narrows into Queen Charlotte Sound, where Pacific whispers turned into full conversation and we pointed for Cape Caution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-five-outside-passage-gamble&quot;&gt;Day Five: Outside Passage Gamble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d gone outside the Fitz Hugh Sound around Calvert Island to Hakai Passage, headed for the Beard Islands bird sanctuary that would lead us to Bella Bella, our required checkpoint. The wind shifted constantly, alternating between pedaling with larger foresails and flying kites when gusts filled in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we reached the island-filled passage to Bella Bella, we were cruising at 5 knots downwind, spotting shell middens along the coast as we gybed down the channel. Cell signal returned with news that we’d gained 10 nautical miles on our competition, though we later learned that Pickle Train had suffered an accident requiring a half-day stop in Bella Bella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The media boat found us again as we passed the halfway mark, and updated weather models convinced us to head back outside for the Pacific route rather than the protected inside passages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-six-sleep-deprivation-and-panic&quot;&gt;Day Six: Sleep Deprivation and Panic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke for a 4am shift to gray seas and zombified exhaustion. After more than 100 hours of sailing in four-hour chunks, sleeping below in rough seas meant hearing every tack as potential equipment failure and every wave break as possible submersion. The stress was accumulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my bunk, I recognized the onset of a panic attack but decided to let it run its course rather than disturb the watch. Our crew operated on rotating shifts of 2 hours “on call” and 4 hours “on watch,” staggered so someone was always fresh. The on-call person would handle duties as needed, then rest. I constantly woke to alarms during shifts, holding on at 4am while another hand steered, often in a dry suit on the high side during rough weather, somehow still falling asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We navigated outside Banks Island through numerous rocks scattered along the coast, dealing with light rain and fog. We discovered leaks around the mast that left our nav table and electronics damp and unreliable. The lack of limber holes in the battery compartment meant 4 inches of water around a non-extinguishable power source until I found a pump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was probably my low point in the race, but the sun rose, meals were shared, and we continued into the final stretches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-seven-the-final-push&quot;&gt;Day Seven: The Final Push&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approaching the US border with cell signal restored, we realized we’d passed Team Narrows Minded, a trimaran whose course track showed an odd series of dips in and out of islands. We were half-pedaling, half-flying big sails, watching the rest of the “kids’ table” fall hours behind us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we rounded the last island (the wrong way) to come into view of Thomas Basin, we dropped the mainsail before crossing the finish line, confusing onlookers. We deployed our pedal system one last time and edged into the cruise ship-shadowed harbor with cowbells ringing and sailors whooping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stepped off the boat to ring the bell, then stood in awkward silence. It was done. Now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked through the crowd shaking hands, thanking fans, talking to teams who’d already finished, learning about their struggles. The “winning” aspect seemed almost beside the point - we were competing against the elements and the course itself. I would have stopped to help other boats just as past racers had stopped for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-r2ak-taught-us&quot;&gt;What R2AK Taught Us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R2AK provided just enough structure to push Kate and me to find a vehicle for achievement and a community to help us along the way. We half-heartedly considered sailing to Haida Gwaii and skipping the finish line - the racing felt secondary to the experience of pushing through challenges together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us remain in a chat thread, continuing conversations that started in those sleepless hours between watches. The race created bonds forged in shared exhaustion, mutual aid, and the peculiar satisfaction of fixing broken things with whatever’s at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WA360 is next June, though we might be in Europe by then. The Three Peaks race (run/sail to high points across the UK) and Fastnet Race are calling. Once you’ve tasted this particular flavor of voluntary suffering combined with extraordinary beauty, it’s hard to go back to ordinary weekend sailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R2AK strips away everything comfortable about sailing and forces you to confront what you’re actually capable of when the alternatives are quitting or figuring it out. Seven days later, with a jury-rigged forestay and a crew that had learned to function on no sleep, we’d proven something to ourselves that’s hard to articulate but impossible to forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cowbells in Ketchikan harbor still ring in my memory, but louder than that is the sound of our crew working together when everything that could go wrong did go wrong, and we kept moving north anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written from the perspective of having completed one of sailing’s most demanding races, with profound respect for the Inside Passage, the other racers, and the communities that make events like R2AK possible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/sailing,/racing,/r2ak,/adventure/2024/06/19/r2ak2024.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/sailing,/racing,/r2ak,/adventure/2024/06/19/r2ak2024.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>sailing,</category>
        
        <category>racing,</category>
        
        <category>r2ak,</category>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Bag June 2022</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blog_posts/OneBag2022.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Gear shot:&lt;/strong&gt; not everything is pictured, some of it I’m wearing :p, but that’s most of what I’m carrying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m on a 2 month trip which will include: working from hotels/cafes/airbnbs (and maybe a client meeting in person), from the US, Kenya, and a few countries in Europe, attending a casual outdoor wedding in Kenya (might buy a shirt for that), hiking in the Pyrenees for 2-3 days, and sailing a day or two; This is what I started with, I’ll update how the trip went when I get home. I write this after two weeks of travel; having already spent a week in Detroit for work and a layover in New York, and am currently in Nairobi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packing thoughts:&lt;/strong&gt; I like the idea of having most things I travel with fit under a plane seat, which ends up being around 20L. Even when I’m skiing, sailing, or climbing; I find that I like something similar to this setup for the majority of my day to day. There are a few things that I change (rain jacket, hiking shoes/socks, leggings) if I’m in a colder or wetter place. I also find on many of those trips I’m brining a carry on bag, and the whole idea of one bagging is negated. That said, this is usually my cary on for those trips either way, so in a way it’s my ‘base’ kit for day to day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;packing&quot;&gt;Packing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REI Flash 22:&lt;/strong&gt; I love this bag, it fits under my airplane seat. I can run with it, and it has enough pockets for water bottles, keys/quick needs, and my kindle/toiletries. I don’t love zippers (they break, get salty when at sea, or get mud/sand in them), and when I have this over stuffed, I can fit my jacket on top with the buckle. This is my 3rd or 4th Flash 22 over the past decade. They do wear out, but for how light they are I’m ok with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;tech&quot;&gt;Tech&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Macbook pro 14 inch:&lt;/strong&gt; I used to worry about my laptop battery, but whatever they updated in this version has the battery running for 8+ hours. I charge my phone off the laptop, and while it’s heavier than my old Macbook pro 13 inch, the battery offset is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pixel 5a:&lt;/strong&gt; Battery lasts long enough for me not to worry as well, and I charge it off my laptop. I don’t know why I like having an apple laptop and an android phone, but I do, and that’s that. I use Google Fi, and haven’t had any major problems while traveling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kindle:&lt;/strong&gt; I find I don’t read as much if I use my phone or an ipad. I tried the Ipad for a trip through the alps, and I did journal with it, but had a hard time reading and falling asleep. The Kindle is easy on the eyes while falling asleep, or reading for days in a tent while it’s raining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bluetooth headphones:&lt;/strong&gt; I like the cord, I find I don’t lose them as I have with the pods. Battery lasts about 10 hours, which is great to travel and being on calls/music all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backup headphones:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve had to use them before, I’d rather have them than not, especially when I forget to charge the others, and I’m on a flight, and there’s a crying baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper/Pens:&lt;/strong&gt; I carry a few sheets of folded paper with me almost anywhere I go along with 2 micron pens. I used to cary a moleskin journal, but didn’t use it enough. The pens are required for passport checks, the papers are just nice to sketch or be away from screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Chargers:
&lt;strong&gt;Apple 65W:&lt;/strong&gt; heavy, but it works, I could get one of the lighter Anker ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB - C cable 6ft:&lt;/strong&gt; I like the L connector for when I work from my lap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2x USB-C cables:&lt;/strong&gt; For charging my phone and headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB-C to USB-mini converter:&lt;/strong&gt; My headphones are usb-mini, and I have used these on other devices. I might get USB-C to USB-A for the times I’m on a plane or rental car and there is only a USB-A connector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;clothing&quot;&gt;Clothing:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;footware&quot;&gt;Footware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luna Falco:&lt;/strong&gt; I wear these almost all the time, I walk, hike, and run in them. They’re supposed to be non-marking… I debate that, but they are still the most versatile footwear I’ve ever had. I get away without bringing socks, and I’ve worn them long enough that I don’t feel my feat all the much… (this is.. good?). If it’s really cold I have these funny softshell slippers with a toe wedge, but I’ve only had to wear those while it was snowing in Montana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soft-goods&quot;&gt;Soft goods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prana Byron:&lt;/strong&gt;I’ve skied from Chamonix to Zermatt in these, I know the Stretch Zion is more suited for that, but these look nicer at dinner, and I can wear them to work events. Brown hides stains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patagonia Nine Trails Shorts:&lt;/strong&gt; Running shorts with mesh. I swim in these too. They have zippers so I’m not worried about dropping my phone while running or hiking. I workout in these in the morning and air them out in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2 light weight Nylon Shirts:&lt;/strong&gt; I think ones a 32Degrees and the other is an Vaori. They don’t smell too bad and I wash them maybe once a week, often while taking a shower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REI Sahara long sleeve:&lt;/strong&gt; I like plaid shirts, and fly fishing shirts seems to work well as sun-shirts, and to take calls where I need a collar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hat:&lt;/strong&gt; A hat from the place I lost my last hat: currently: San Juan, Washington. People like to comment on islands, and there are lots of sailors there. It’s been the start of more than one converstaion. I wonder where I’ll lose it, and find the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Glasses:&lt;/strong&gt; Aviators, nothing special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Underwear:&lt;/strong&gt; Coolmax. I wear my shorts when running and they have a mesh liner, I wash these every once in a while, doesn’t seem to be an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REI Flash Jacket:&lt;/strong&gt; Similar to the Hoodini, except it has pockets! I first wore my Patagonia Hoodini on my Haught Route trip, and found it incredible. It’s the perfect mix of wearable in wind while active that would be too warm for the light puffy, and layers well over the puffy when it’s raining. Not great for a downpour, but I would bring my gore-tex if this was a trip where I was going more remote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arc Teryx Atom LT:&lt;/strong&gt; I had the Patagonia Nano Air hoody, and It was by far my favorite jacket. I wore it for probably 3, maybe 4 years, and it just got too compressed. I’m trying the Atom to see how it compares. If it’s anything similar, then I can wear it up to 14,000 ft peaks, in high wind, and not feel too warm while at the airport (like I can in my down jackets). Also I find it cozy like cotton hoodies, and I don’t find down jackets to be. yes it’s expensive, but it’s basically the one jacket I know I can bring anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other&quot;&gt;Other:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water bottle:&lt;/strong&gt; Hydro Flask Stainless Steel Travel Mug: I drink tea from this mug all day, it makes me happy. I carry it hiking, and if I need more water I bring a smart water bottle or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dry Bag:&lt;/strong&gt; Nice to store phone/wallet in if I’m in the rain or kayaking or w/e. I’ve used it enough to keep it with me over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toiletries:&lt;/strong&gt; Small plastic bag for contacts, tooth brush, and floss, and glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deodorant/Sunscreen:&lt;/strong&gt; Am human, do burn and smell.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2022 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/travel/onebag/minimalism/2022/05/29/onebag.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/travel/onebag/minimalism/2022/05/29/onebag.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>travel</category>
        
        <category>onebag</category>
        
        <category>minimalism</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Testing all the things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 16:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/helloworld/2022/02/05/helloworld.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/helloworld/2022/02/05/helloworld.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>helloworld</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring Virtual Depths - How to Play with Your Comfort Zone</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;exploring-virtual-depths-how-to-play-with-your-comfort-zone&quot;&gt;Exploring Virtual Depths: How to Play with Your Comfort Zone&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of ‘type 2 fun’ was introduced to me when I first went caving: “it’s like fun but different.” Type 1 fun is fun now and fun later; type 2 is not fun now, but ‘fun’ later - a struggle that was worth it, delayed gratification toward pursuits you’re striving for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-perfect-teacher&quot;&gt;The Perfect Teacher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently found a game that mastered this progression like nothing I’ve ever experienced: Subnautica. It’s a survival game based on an aquatic alien planet that refuses to give you useful weapons and creates situations requiring you to constantly face your fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re dropped onto an ocean planet in the literal shallows with your life raft as home base. You can see the ocean floor a few feet below, you’re given little instruction, and you have the constraints of needing food, water, and oxygen, which creates time pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-progression-system&quot;&gt;The Progression System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 1: Normalize the shallow&lt;/strong&gt;
The shallows are safe. There are a few aggressive animals, but they don’t chase you far - they’re protective of their space, not enemies. You could ‘die,’ but that’s not really the challenge. Subnautica creates a comfortable, safe space to normalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 2: Venture deeper&lt;/strong&gt;
After a few hours, you realize the game requires you to venture deeper into your environment. Not only are there different resources and objectives, but there are new creatures… and it gets darker. You’re scuba diving at hundreds of meters with air supply, food, and safety concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stage 3: Master the unknown&lt;/strong&gt;
The ‘levels’ have more to do with whether you’ve upgraded your character or created ways to survive underwater. Often a new environment becomes available (it always was), and it’s scary - there’s a creature that moves too fast, you don’t know how to fend them off, and you’re time-stressed because you’re running out of oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-learning-cycle&quot;&gt;The Learning Cycle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as you keep going, you realize how the creature moves, you increase your air capacity, and you find new safe spots. You begin to understand your mental map (none is provided), and you aren’t wasting time going the inefficient way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;: You take in lots of data to create comfort and set a baseline for normal. That’s stressful, that’s outside your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then&lt;/strong&gt;: You find your safe speed, stability, and inch forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finally&lt;/strong&gt;: This process repeats as the game finds ways to challenge your progress with greater depths and more formidable creatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;real-world-application&quot;&gt;Real-World Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subnautica is a game, but real life isn’t - if you were diving hundreds of feet down and ‘mess up,’ you die. Which is why creating safe spaces to explore and tune your comfort dial from underwhelmed to overwhelmed, and then into the just-right ‘flow,’ is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ice-climbing-example&quot;&gt;Ice Climbing Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, I attended an ice climbing festival with friends. All of us were climbers, and I had dabbled in ice climbing but had never led a serious pitch. The festival offers gear with classes to demo, giving you an environment to take you out of your comfort zone safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the four of us, we all took different paths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Those with the least experience stayed in guided classes on top rope all three days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Others with more experience were off on their own by the weekend’s end, climbing routes and experimenting with techniques we’d learned the day before&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were all turning our comfort dials, exploring what the right level of challenge was for us, finding type 2 fun and getting into flow - with too much stress letting us know to back off, and boredom as a gauge of when to try something harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-framework&quot;&gt;The Framework&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find your baseline&lt;/strong&gt; in a new environment; wade in slowly. Jumping in can lead to stress and being overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slowly normalize&lt;/strong&gt; and gain awareness of the important cues of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take small steps&lt;/strong&gt; with consistent check-ins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Play with boundaries&lt;/strong&gt; - go deeper and track your response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always keep enough oxygen&lt;/strong&gt; to get back to the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re exploring a new location yourself or hosting an environment for others, create your safe space and play with the boundaries. It’s a series of small steps that push you just outside your comfort zone - far enough to grow, but not so far that you’re overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/gaming/psychology/adventure/2020/09/29/comfort-zone-post.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/gaming/psychology/adventure/2020/09/29/comfort-zone-post.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>gaming</category>
        
        <category>psychology</category>
        
        <category>adventure</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fall 2019 Intention Setting and Life Update</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;fall-2019-intention-setting-and-life-update&quot;&gt;Fall 2019 Intention Setting and Life Update&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Friends and Family!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Fall 2019, and I thought it’s been long enough since I sent out an all-comms update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;catching-up&quot;&gt;Catching Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite the year - in fact, it’s been quite the year and a half. As most of you know, Kate and I left San Francisco last summer and spent the following period in Europe and Africa. I’ll cut it off at the start of 2019, but to keep it short:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Major Adventures:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climbed the glaciated Mt. Stanley, the high point of Uganda and the DRC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Saw chimpanzees in the Central African rainforest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climbed Mt. Kenya via the 20-pitch 5.8 route at 17,000 ft (the 2nd highest point in Africa)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attended the online altMBA program&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participated in AfrikaBurn as a construction hand on Octocrab and became an AfrikaBurn Ranger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent Travels:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spent time in Mauritius&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went sailing in Greece for two weeks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had a month back in the US&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Returned to Kenya, packed up the house, sold everything&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Went hiking around Scotland and the Manchester area for two weeks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burning Man 2019:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passed Black Rock Ranger alpha certification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assisted as a Green Dot ranger (helping those in overwhelmed states)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Camped with Burners Without Borders as co-build lead of their 100-person camp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-now&quot;&gt;The Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m back in San Francisco with Kate, where she’s leading IDEO’s build of the Digital Dream Lab. We’re looking for housing in San Francisco while I search for my next career opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re staying with friends around the San Francisco and potentially Oakland area. House hunting in SF isn’t all that fun, and I don’t recommend it - especially when one of you has a job! It’s been stressful, to be honest, and we might find a less-than-ideal situation to allow me to focus on job searches and work that comes up in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;job-search-focus&quot;&gt;Job Search Focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job-wise, I’m looking for a way to work with a group that’s facing challenging problems in the environmental and generative space. Ocean tech is attractive at the moment, but I’ve also been looking at energy companies and groups that are making hardware tools to better solve problems that cause industrial waste and affect how we consume and generate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past half-decade, I’ve learned how to lead hardware engineering projects with mechanical systems and electronic development. I see myself as understanding how to build and would like to play in the human engineering side - working with teams and understanding problem spaces, rather than only building on the engineering side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that’s broad: I want to help people solve problems with systems, automation, and teams. I’m job searching. If you think my background would be attractive to a group or person you know, I’d love to be in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-next-3-months&quot;&gt;The Next 3 Months&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current ‘day job’ is job searching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Projects:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spending time climbing at Mission Cliffs in the mornings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planning to run 100 miles in October while also not drinking that month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participating in Inktober (daily drawing challenge)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule Constraints:&lt;/strong&gt;
Kate is taking a yoga class during the weekends, so we won’t be traveling until December. This forces me into focusing 10+ hours minimum on weekends on my side projects (and intentionally not looking for jobs during that time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intention-setting-philosophy&quot;&gt;Intention Setting Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is my calendar of ‘intent’ - we’ll see how that all goes; I’ll let you know December 21st!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This connects to my broader goal-setting system that I’ve been refining over the years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Circle Concept:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve always thought of the calendar as a circle, maybe from a calendar I saw in elementary school. With the New Year at the bottom and Spring/Summer at the top, like a clock. When I plan my years, it looks like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend told me he extrapolated it into a helix seen from two dimensions with the years flowing into each other. A calendar helps you see how much time any one item takes. I work in weeks and weekends - if the goal I have can’t be worked on once a week or weekend (lots of my goals are trips), then it’s not approachable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systems Over Goals:&lt;/strong&gt; Quantity over quality leads to quality (draw 20 pictures to get to your 3 masterpieces).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning Principles:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan like you need it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a lot of plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accept that you can only do one thing at a time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commit to a few of them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turn it into a system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set a due date&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create accountability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get excited about it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put it on paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tell those who matter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One step a day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-challenges&quot;&gt;Current Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Housing:&lt;/strong&gt; San Francisco real estate is brutal, especially when trying to coordinate two careers and social connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Career Transition:&lt;/strong&gt; Moving from hands-on engineering to more strategic/systems thinking roles requires finding the right opportunity and team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Balancing Act:&lt;/strong&gt; Managing job search intensity with personal projects and relationship needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few months are about finding the right opportunity that aligns with my values and experience. I’m looking for work that combines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical challenge:&lt;/strong&gt; Problems that require systems thinking and engineering solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Work that addresses climate change and sustainability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team leadership:&lt;/strong&gt; Opportunities to help groups solve complex problems together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community benefit:&lt;/strong&gt; Projects that serve broader social good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-from-the-road&quot;&gt;Lessons from the Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year and a half of travel and adventure reinforced some key insights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adventure builds perspective:&lt;/strong&gt; Climbing mountains in Africa and sailing in Greece reminded me that most day-to-day stress is self-created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community is everything:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether it’s rangers at Burning Man or sailing crews in Greece, the best experiences happen when people work together toward shared goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systems thinking applies everywhere:&lt;/strong&gt; From organizing 100-person camps to navigating African bureaucracy, understanding how systems work (and don’t work) is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Constraints breed creativity:&lt;/strong&gt; Limited resources and challenging environments often produce the most innovative solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bigger-picture&quot;&gt;The Bigger Picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This transition period is really about aligning career with values. After years of building technical skills and gaining experience, I want to work on problems that matter with people who share similar values around sustainability, community, and systems thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job search isn’t just about finding employment - it’s about finding the right platform to apply everything I’ve learned about engineering, community building, and problem-solving to challenges that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-you-can-help&quot;&gt;How You Can Help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know of opportunities in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ocean technology and environmental monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sustainable energy and industrial efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hardware companies focused on environmental solutions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teams working on climate change adaptation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organizations building tools for community resilience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to connect. I’m particularly interested in roles that combine technical problem-solving with team leadership and strategic thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;staying-connected&quot;&gt;Staying Connected&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll send updates on how this all unfolds. If you’re in the San Francisco area and want to catch up over coffee or a climb, let me know. If you’re elsewhere and planning adventures, keep me in the loop - there’s always room for one more sailor, climber, or community builder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for following along on this journey. The adventure continues, just in a different format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resume and portfolio:&lt;/strong&gt; Available upon request&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn:&lt;/strong&gt; [Your profile here]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current projects:&lt;/strong&gt; Adventure Report (still running monthly), various sailing expeditions in planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calendar of intent for the next quarter is ambitious but achievable. By December 21st, I’ll know how well this intention-setting approach worked for a major life transition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Set intention, invite specifically, show up, and grow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt;
If you think my background would be attractive to a group or person you know, here’s my contact information and general approach to the work I’m seeking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to the next chapter!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/life-update/planning/reflection/2019/09/20/2019-Intention.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/life-update/planning/reflection/2019/09/20/2019-Intention.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>life-update</category>
        
        <category>planning</category>
        
        <category>reflection</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Letter to an Aspiring Mountaineer</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-letter-to-an-aspiring-mountaineer&quot;&gt;A Letter to an Aspiring Mountaineer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A competent mountaineer knows how to lead, and going up with guides whose intention is guiding (not instructing) won’t get you there. Following guides doesn’t build leading skills when teaching you to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big mountains are sexy, but often not the places you learn to lead. It’s the repetition of skills, the building of a risk model, and the communities that give you constructive feedback and push you to expand your boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-stages-of-learning&quot;&gt;The Three Stages of Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shu-state-following-the-form&quot;&gt;Shu State: Following the Form&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good way to start is by setting a baseline of agreed-upon actions (this is known as the ‘shu’ state in zen). Do as you’re told (always use this knot) and apply it to your environment. It’s important to stay within bounds when you don’t understand the boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the following-a-guide state, and it isn’t a one-time thing - it applies for each new skill you learn. You’re always going back to the beginning; each new surface to climb, each new language to speak, each new tool to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ha-state-experimenting-with-jazz&quot;&gt;Ha State: Experimenting with Jazz&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you’ve followed the form long enough and have defined the risks and uses of the skill, you realize you want to lead. You progress into the chasm of novice-intermediate syndrome, where you need to push your own boundaries and experiment to understand what the forms and ‘truths’ mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s asking for instruction and then going out on your own. It’s finding the boundaries yourself and suffering consequences of missteps that a guide would never let you take. It’s building understanding of how far you want to push yourself and how you want to interact with others as your followers, equals, and betters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is known as the ‘Ha’ state in zen - putting jazz into your step. Seeing that the strict form was there for a reason, but that poetry has a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ri-state-mastering-the-philosophy&quot;&gt;Ri State: Mastering the Philosophy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, you’ll make it out. You’ll see that the long dark valley of effort, obscurity, hardship, and frustrating arguments over… what? It might end in you leaving, but if you keep going, you’ll be in the ‘Ri.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The master who understood why the forms were important, who saw why leaving them is necessary, and who experimented with different hows and whys. The ‘Ri’ no longer needs to follow the forms because every act is instilled with the underlying philosophy of intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-your-community&quot;&gt;Finding Your Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where community helps - where the helpers are looking for the next generation and those who’ve crossed the commitment barriers. This is where time and energy need to be invested, and nothing but effort will give you understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find that fire that warms you. Find the camp with your right mentors, and pay them. Sometimes they need money, sometimes companionship, sometimes just a friend or student or someone to listen. But contribute, learn, and give back. Help keep that fire going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-hard-truths&quot;&gt;The Hard Truths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The summit photo doesn’t prove much.&lt;/strong&gt; Experienced climbers have turned around more than they’ve summited and have waited for days in small tents and cold huts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We don’t ‘have’ to do this.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s a sport of ego; we choose to do it, so go with heart and go for the right reasons - your reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The mountains will still be there.&lt;/strong&gt; There’s no rush except the one you create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forward&quot;&gt;The Path Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep learning, talk to the old-timers, and be careful of the bold. Find a mentor willing to teach you so you can then lead yourself. Find the community that allows safe experimentation, is open, wants new members, and wants them to go places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be interested - the hard work isn’t sexy. Show up every week and make sure people know where and who’s welcome. The secret isn’t in the gear or the routes; it’s in the consistency and the community you build around shared experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mountains teach patience, humility, and the value of preparation. But most importantly, they teach you that the best adventures are shared ones, and the skills you learn can be applied far beyond the peaks you climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Set intention, invite specifically, show up, and grow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2019 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/mountaineering/advice/learning/2019/03/14/Aspiring-Mountaineer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/mountaineering/advice/learning/2019/03/14/Aspiring-Mountaineer.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
        <category>advice</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
